<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Code Yarns Tech Blog</title>
    <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/</link>
    <description>Online journal of posts about computers and fixes to common issues.</description>
    <atom:link href="https://codeyarns.com/tech/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 22:46:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Google Gemini</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2026-01-21-google-gemini.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://gemini.google.com/app"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google Gemini&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a popular AI assistant and the official one from Google.
It has quickly become my replacement of search engines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the web&lt;/strong&gt;: It can be used in any browser by visiting &lt;a href="https://gemini.google.com/app"&gt;gemini.google.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;iOS app&lt;/strong&gt;:
Install from the App Store &lt;a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/google-gemini/id6477489729"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MacOS app&lt;/strong&gt;:
There is no official app, so I create a web app instead.
Open &lt;a href="https://gemini.google.com/app"&gt;gemini.google.com&lt;/a&gt; in Google Chrome, choose Save and Share -&amp;gt; Install Page as App.
After this Google Gemini is available as a MacOS app to open and run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2026-01-21-google-gemini.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 22:37:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NetNewsWire</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2026-01-12-netnewswire.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://netnewswire.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NetNewsWire&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a highly-acclaimed classic RSS reader for MacOS, iPhone and iPad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install&lt;/strong&gt;:
For MacOS, download and install the ZIP file from its website.
For iPhone/iPad, go to the App Store and install it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add feeds&lt;/strong&gt;:
Provide the website URL that has the feed or the RSS/ATOM feed URL.
By default, the feeds are downloaded and maintained locally on your device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sync&lt;/strong&gt;:
To sync between MacOS and iPhone/iPad, we need to use iCloud or the FreshRSS self-hosted feed aggregator.
I found that the sync is super-slow through iCloud.
For FreshRSS, provide the credentials and API URL as specified &lt;a href="2026-01-12-freshrss.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
I think FreshRSS is the best option, since I can read my feeds on my iPhone, on my Macbook and also continue reading on my home Linux computer (through the self-hosted FreshRSS URL).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2026-01-12-netnewswire.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 04:17:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FreshRSS</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2026-01-12-freshrss.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.freshrss.org/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FreshRSS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a free RSS feed aggregator that can be used to read RSS feeds online and also exposes an API that can be used with desktop/mobile RSS apps.
Its source code can be &lt;a href="https://github.com/FreshRSS/FreshRSS"&gt;seen on Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Install&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of using it from source code, I find it easier to use its pre-built Docker container.
To get it running from Docker container:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prepare the Docker packages and user setup:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo apt install -y docker.io docker-compose
$ sudo usermod -aG docker $USER
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Log out and log back in for group changes to take effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a directory for it and enter it:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ mkdir ~/freshrss
$ cd ~/freshrss
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a &lt;code&gt;~/freshrss/docker-compose.yml&lt;/code&gt; file and add these lines to it:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;code&gt;version: '2.4'
services:
  freshrss:
    image: freshrss/freshrss:latest
    container_name: freshrss
    hostname: freshrss
    restart: unless-stopped
    logging:
      options:
        max-size: 10m
    volumes:
      - ./data:/var/www/FreshRSS/data
      - ./extensions:/var/www/FreshRSS/extensions
    environment:
      TZ: America/Los_Angeles  # Change to your timezone
      CRON_MIN: '*/20'         # Checks for updates every 20 mins
    ports:
      - &amp;quot;80:80&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launch the container:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ docker-compose up -d
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;code&gt;http://&amp;lt;public-ip&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; to access the FreshRSS online setup wizard for the first time.
You will need to provide a &lt;em&gt;login&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;password&lt;/em&gt;.
Go with default options and let it pick &lt;code&gt;SQLite&lt;/code&gt; as the database to make life easy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Usage&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In your browser, go to &lt;code&gt;http://&amp;lt;public-ip&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.
You can add feeds, that appear under &lt;em&gt;Uncategorized&lt;/em&gt; category unless you create and move them to new categories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;API access&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To read RSS feeds from desktop and mobile apps through FreshRSS, we need to enable API access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the online interface go to the gear icon in the top-right corner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Authentication&lt;/em&gt;, enable &lt;em&gt;Allow API access&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Profile&lt;/em&gt;, go to API password and add a password.
Go to &lt;code&gt;http://&amp;lt;public-ip&amp;gt;/api/&lt;/code&gt; to check the API access is working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to your RSS application and provide the username, API password and the API path.
For Google Reader compatible API, the path is &lt;code&gt;http://&amp;lt;public-ip&amp;gt;/api/greader.php&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;API access can be used by your favorite application to add or remove feeds, mark as read or favorite and all other normal operations possible through the FreshRSS UI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2026-01-12-freshrss.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 03:59:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oracle Cloud Infrastructure</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2026-01-12-oracle-cloud-infrastructure.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.oracle.com/cloud/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oracle Cloud Infrastructure (OCI)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is one of the largest Cloud Service Providers (CSP) of the world.
It offers a &lt;a href="https://www.oracle.com/cloud/free/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Free Tier&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that is great for home users who have minimal need of a cloud instance.
The rest of the information on this page is based on my experience with the Free Tier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Create an account&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the Free Tier page, follow the online direction to create a new account.
You will be required to provide details of a valid credit card, but it will not be charged.
You will need to associate an &lt;em&gt;email address&lt;/em&gt;, but also create an &lt;em&gt;account name&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the account creation was not immediate, it took a day and I could verify my login worked only after a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Create an instance&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An instance is the first step to get access to a compute node where we can install and run software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From top-left menu, go to Compute -&amp;gt; Instances and choose &lt;em&gt;Create instance&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Placement&lt;/strong&gt;, I let it pick the default that was &lt;code&gt;pamH:US-SANJOSE-1-AD-1&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Image&lt;/strong&gt;, I chose &lt;code&gt;Canonical Ubuntu 24.04&lt;/code&gt;.
I noticed that both Oracle Linux and Canoncial Ubuntu images were all listed as &lt;em&gt;Free&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Shape&lt;/strong&gt;, I let it pick the default &lt;code&gt;VM.Standard.E2.1.Micro&lt;/code&gt; since that was the only one marked as &lt;em&gt;Always Free-eligible&lt;/em&gt;.
This came with a 1-core CPU, 1 GB memory and 0.48 Gbps network bandwidth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Networking&lt;/strong&gt; section, under &lt;em&gt;Primary VNIC&lt;/em&gt; I used the default options of &lt;em&gt;Select existing virtual cloud network&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Select existing subnet&lt;/em&gt;.
Since we need a public IP address to SSH to, I enabled the &lt;em&gt;Automatically assign public IPv4 address&lt;/em&gt; option.
In the &lt;em&gt;Add SSH keys&lt;/em&gt; section, I pasted my public SSH key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The instance creation took 5 minutes and the instance was listed as &lt;em&gt;Running&lt;/em&gt;.
Note the username (default was &lt;code&gt;ubuntu&lt;/code&gt; in my case) and the &lt;em&gt;public IP&lt;/em&gt; address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt;
The first instance I created did not have the public IP option enabled for choosing.
I messed with the firewall (see below), deleted this instance, created a new instance and it had the public IP option.
Go figure!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Configure the firewall&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All incoming web traffic is blocked by default.
To enable incoming traffic at certain ports, we must open them in the OCI firewall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From top-left menu, go to Networking -&amp;gt; Virtual cloud networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the list, choose your VCN and go to its &lt;em&gt;Security&lt;/em&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;Security Lists&lt;/em&gt; section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click on the &lt;em&gt;Default Security List&lt;/em&gt; -&amp;gt; Security rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click on &lt;em&gt;Add Ingress Rules&lt;/em&gt; and provide &lt;em&gt;Source CIDR&lt;/em&gt; as &lt;code&gt;0.0.0.0/0&lt;/code&gt;, IP protocol as &lt;code&gt;TCP&lt;/code&gt;, Destination ports as &lt;code&gt;80,443&lt;/code&gt; (or the ports required by your web application) and allow both HTTP and HTTPS traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;SSS to the instance&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To SSH to the public IP address of the instance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ssh -i &amp;lt;path-to-private-key&amp;gt; ubuntu@&amp;lt;public-ip&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can now work in this compute instance by installing Ubuntu packages, install Docker images and work as if at a local Ubuntu computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Access web application&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To run a web application, install it and then access it through the browser at the address &lt;code&gt;http://&amp;lt;public-ip&amp;gt;/&lt;/code&gt;.
If there a API exposed by the app, then &lt;code&gt;http://&amp;lt;public-ip&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;api-path&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2026-01-12-oracle-cloud-infrastructure.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 03:10:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Firefox Cheatsheet</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2026-01-08-firefox-cheatsheet.html</link>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/ai-chatbot"&gt;Use AI Chatbots&lt;/a&gt;:
Press &lt;code&gt;⌃ x&lt;/code&gt; (MacOS) or &lt;code&gt;Ctrl Alt x&lt;/code&gt; (Linux) to toggle the &lt;strong&gt;AI chatbot&lt;/strong&gt; sidebar on the left.
The first time it will ask you to pick from the various chatbots like Google Gemini, ChatGPT and others.
In addition to directly using the AI chatbot sidebar, I find it useful to highlight text on a webpage and click the ✨ (sparkles) button that appears beside the text to feed it to the AI chatbot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2026-01-08-firefox-cheatsheet.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 23:07:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tech links of January 2026</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2026-01-06-tech-links-of-january-2026.html</link>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tonsky.me/blog/tahoe-icons/"&gt;It’s hard to justify Tahoe icons&lt;/a&gt;:
Damning post on how MacOS Tahoe is overloaded with tiny, meaningless, inconsistent UI icons.
Apple seems to have completely forgotten its own 1992 HIG.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://sqlite.org/whyc.html"&gt;Why SQLite is written in C&lt;/a&gt;:
C is fast, compatible with all libraries and can be written in an object-oriented manner (if required).
Provides a list of requirements for Rust before it will be considered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://addyosmani.com/blog/21-lessons/"&gt;21 Lessons From 14 Years at Google&lt;/a&gt;: Solid list of learnings, matched a lot with my experience in big tech companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The best engineers are obsessed with solving user problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being right is cheap. Getting to right together is the real work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bias towards action. Ship. You can edit a bad page, but you can’t edit a blank one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clarity is seniority. Cleverness is overhead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Novelty is a loan you repay in outages, hiring, and cognitive overhead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your code doesn’t advocate for you. People do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The best code is the code you never had to write.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At scale, even your bugs have users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most “slow” teams are actually misaligned teams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on what you can control. Ignore what you can’t.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abstractions don’t remove complexity. They move it to the day you’re on call.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing forces clarity. The fastest way to learn something better is to try teaching it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The work that makes other work possible is priceless - and invisible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you win every debate, you’re probably accumulating silent resistance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When a measure becomes a target, it stops measuring.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Admitting what you don’t know creates more safety than pretending you do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your network outlasts every job you’ll ever have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most performance wins come from removing work, not adding cleverness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process exists to reduce uncertainty, not to create paper trails.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eventually, time becomes worth more than money. Act accordingly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no shortcuts, but there is compounding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://jvns.ca/blog/2024/09/12/reasons-i--still--love-fish/"&gt;Reasons I still love the fish shell&lt;/a&gt;:
All the same reasons why I have been using Fish as my default shell since 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Dec/31/the-year-in-llms/"&gt;2025: The year in LLMs&lt;/a&gt;:
Simon Willison's mega summary of 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2026-01-06-tech-links-of-january-2026.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 22:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to self host Google Fonts</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2026-01-01-how-to-self-host-google-fonts.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bored with using regular fonts for my website, I finally decided to try &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_typography#Web_fonts"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;web fonts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_Fonts"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google Fonts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; seems to be the preferred choice of web fonts since it has more than 1500 open-source fonts.
I did not want every load of my webpages to pull in the font file from Google servers, so I looked for a way to self host the font files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the Google fonts are available in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TrueType"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TTF&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; format.
These files are large and the recommended lightweight file format for website is apparently &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_Open_Font_Format"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web Open Font Format 2.0 (WOFF2)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found the website &lt;a href="https://gwfh.mranftl.com/fonts"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google Webfonts Helper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, created by &lt;a href="https://mranftl.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mario Ranftl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, to be a one-stop resource for self-hosting Google fonts.
I can pick a font and select charsets and styles to view how the font rendering looks.
For the selected styles, it gave me the &lt;code&gt;font-face&lt;/code&gt; definition CSS that I would need to add to my CSS file.
Furthermore, it also provides a download of the &lt;code&gt;.woff2&lt;/code&gt; font files for the chosen charsets and styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self-hosting these web fonts was easy with the Google Webfonts Helper:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose the font, charsets and styles for which you need the WOFF2 files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copy the CSS font face definition to your CSS file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In your CSS formatting, use the new font name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download the WOFF2 files and place them in &lt;code&gt;fonts/&lt;/code&gt; directory of your website.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upload the new CSS file and the font files to your website and the newly rendered webpage should be using them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2026-01-01-how-to-self-host-google-fonts.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 20:00:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Curious Case of the Missing English Subtitles</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2026-01-01-the-curious-case-of-the-missing-english-subtitles.html</link>
      <description>&lt;h1&gt;Problem&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deciding to educate myself, I recently picked up a 10-DVD box set of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star_Trek:_The_Original_Series_season_1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Star Trek: The Original Series (Season 1)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
I plopped the first DVD into a &lt;a href="https://electronics.sony.com/tv-video/blu-ray-dvd-players/dvd-players/p/dvpsr510h"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sony DVP-SR510H&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; player that was connected over HDMI to a &lt;a href="https://www.hisense-usa.com/product-page/televisions-55-inch-a6-series-led-4k-uhd-smart-google-tv-2021-55a65h"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hisense 55A6H&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; TV running &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Android_TV#Google_TV_interface"&gt;Google TV&lt;/a&gt;.
The remastered video and audio sounded great, but the DVD did not seem to have English subtitles.
It only had French and Spanish subtitles and when chosen those were displayed correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many years now, I have relied on English subtitles when watching TV series and movies.
It seemed surprising that the release of such a popular TV series would be missing English subtitles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Solution&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the back of the box, it had the logos for &lt;strong&gt;CC (Closed Captions)&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;NTSC&lt;/strong&gt;.
I already knew that CC was information transmitted along with the analog TV signals.
And since Star Trek was a TV series, it made sense that the DVD creators decided to retain the original CC info transmitted over NTSC video in the discs.
How to get this CC info out from the DVD and display on the TV?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Checking online, I found that this CC info &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; be transmitted over HDMI.
So, I hooked up the 3-color &lt;strong&gt;component video cable&lt;/strong&gt; that has yellow (for video) and red-white (for right-left audio) to the DVD player and the TV.
In the TV inputs, I chose &lt;em&gt;AV&lt;/em&gt; and I knew I was getting NTSC video since it was noticeably lower quality than HDMI video.
However, no CC info was displayed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I dug into the Google TV settings for CC and enabled all of it.
This is Settings -&amp;gt; Accessibility -&amp;gt; Captions.
Still no CC info!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I suspected that the DVD player was messing with the raw analog output before sending it to the TV.
So, I dove into its screen setup -&amp;gt; Mode (Progressive) and changed from &lt;em&gt;Auto&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Video&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I was able to see the original English version of Closed Captions on the Star Trek video!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: The same trick did not work on my portable &lt;strong&gt;Sony DVP-FX950&lt;/strong&gt; DVD player.
Probably because it is only sending digital video to its internal display and does not have any option to use the analog video info.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2026-01-01-the-curious-case-of-the-missing-english-subtitles.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 01:20:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JankyBorders</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-11-05-jankyborders.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Something I miss from older versions of Windows is clear indication of which window is currently in focus.
In MacOS Tahoe, the only indication of the window in focus is that its traffic light buttons are in color, while they are greyed out for the rest of the windows.
&lt;a href="https://github.com/FelixKratz/JankyBorders"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JankyBorders&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is an open-source app that helps draw a colored border around the currently focused window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ brew tap FelixKratz/formulae
$ brew install borders
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Test the app&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To test the app from the terminal with a thick green border:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ borders width=10 active_color=0xFF00FF00
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To run as service&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First create a configuration file &lt;code&gt;~/.config/borders/bordersrc&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;code&gt;#!/bin/bash

options=(
    width=10
    active_color=0xFF00FF00
)

borders &amp;quot;${options[@]}&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next run as service in the background:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ brew services start borders
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tried with:&lt;/strong&gt; JankyBorders 1.8.4 and MacOS Tahoe 26.0.1&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-11-05-jankyborders.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 14:37:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preview Cheatsheet</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-10-30-preview-cheatsheet.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preview&lt;/strong&gt; is the default application in MacOS to view images and PDF files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;PDF files&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Highlight&lt;/strong&gt;:
Choose View -&amp;gt; Show Markup toolbar so that it is visible at the top.
Mark the lines with the mouse cursor and choose the &lt;em&gt;Highlight&lt;/em&gt; button in the Markup toolbar.
Keyboard shortcut is to mark the lines and press &lt;code&gt;control command h&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-10-30-preview-cheatsheet.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 19:43:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Garmin Instinct 2S Solar</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-09-27-garmin-instinct-2s-solar.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Disappointed by the &lt;a href="2025-09-21-apple-watch-se-3.html"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apple Watch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I was looking for a smartwatch with longer battery life and a size that fits my small wrist and discovered &lt;a href="https://www.garmin.com/en-US/p/741462/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Garmin Instinct 2S Solar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
This watch turned out to have the softest, most comfortable strap I have ever tried and its closely spaced holes make it easy to have a great fit on the wrist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Buttons&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 5 buttons, 3 on the left and 2 on the right:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CTRL/Light: Single-press to toggle the backlight. Double-press to toggle the flashlight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Menu/Up: Hold to view menu.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ABC/Down: Hold to view Altimeter, Barometer and Compass screen (ABC).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GPS: &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set/Back: Press to return to previous screen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Glances&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Press Up and Down buttons to scroll through the Glances.
Info shown includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solar intensity graph&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weather&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sunrise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Last Sport&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heart rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measure heart rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sleep&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calendar &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notifications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Watch faces&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The watch ships with a few faces and many more can be found online and installed to the watch by using the &lt;strong&gt;ConnectIQ&lt;/strong&gt; app on the iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Change watch face&lt;/strong&gt;:
Long press the Menu button and choose Watch Face.
Scroll up and down through the various watch faces.
Many of the watch faces have a &lt;em&gt;Customize&lt;/em&gt; option that lets you customize the face.
Some of the watch faces can be customized only through the ConnectIQ app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instinct Pro&lt;/strong&gt;:
This is a watch face that I like for this watch.
It can be found and installed using the ConnectIQ app.
Note that it can only be customized using the app.
Documentation for the watch face can be found &lt;a href="https://reed.works/2022/06/12/instinct-pro/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Software&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://connect.garmin.com/"&gt;Garmin Connect&lt;/a&gt;: Smartphone app for the watch. Recommended method to sync with the watch and track health stats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://apps.garmin.com/en-US/"&gt;Garmin ConnectIQ&lt;/a&gt;: To discover and install apps and watch faces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.garmin.com/en-US/software/express/"&gt;Garmin Express&lt;/a&gt;: Windows/MacOS software for working with the watch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Garmin Pay&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open Garmin Connect app, press on your watch (top right corner), press on &amp;gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose Wallet &amp;amp; Garmin Pay and add a new card.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Usage&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sync time&lt;/strong&gt;:
Hold down Set button until the options show up.
Choose &lt;em&gt;Set time with GPS&lt;/em&gt;.
Note that even though I tried this, my watch was 3 seconds faster than the actual time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disable heart rate monitor&lt;/strong&gt;:
Hold menu button to get to menu options.
Choose &lt;em&gt;Sensors &amp;amp; Accessories&lt;/em&gt; -&amp;gt; Wrist Heart Rate and change Status to off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-09-27-garmin-instinct-2s-solar.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 03:44:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Apple Watch SE 3</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-09-21-apple-watch-se-3.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apple Watch SE 3&lt;/strong&gt; is a smartwatch launched by Apple in 2025.
Of the 2 sizes available for this watch, I picked the 40mm case for my small wrist.
I used the watch for a week and decided to return it due to reasons detailed later below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digital crown&lt;/strong&gt;:
Press to see the watch screen or Home screen.
Double-click to open the App Switcher.
Turn to scroll what is on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Side button&lt;/strong&gt;:
Press to use Control Center.
Double-click for Apple Pay.
Press and hold to power down or power up the watch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Change watch face&lt;/strong&gt;:
Long press on the watch face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;View date and day&lt;/strong&gt;:
A surprisingly few watch faces show the date and day.
In the default screen, swipe up from the bottom to see the date and day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;View widgets&lt;/strong&gt;:
Swipe up from the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Silent mode&lt;/strong&gt;:
Press the side button to open Control Center.
Press the bell icon to enable silent mode.
Only vibrations will be allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get hourly vibration&lt;/strong&gt;:
On the watch go to Settings -&amp;gt; Accessibility -&amp;gt; Chimes.
Enable Chimes and schedule for once an hour/30/15 minutes.
This plays a sound, but will use a haptic vibration if the watch is set to silent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Display the Activity app&lt;/strong&gt;:
Confusingly the Activity app is also displayed as Fitness app in some places in the watch.
This app was missing in my watch and it took a while to figure out why.
I had disabled this app on my iPhone and so it was also hidden on my watch.
On the iPhone, go to Settings -&amp;gt; Screen Time -&amp;gt; Content &amp;amp; Privacy Restrictions -&amp;gt; Allowed Apps &amp;amp; Features and enable the Fitness app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sync the alarms from iPhone&lt;/strong&gt;:
The only alarms that are synced from iPhone are the special &lt;em&gt;sleep&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;wake up&lt;/em&gt; alarms.
None of the normal alarms from the iPhone are synced to the phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google TV remote&lt;/strong&gt;:
On the iPhone, I like controlling our smart TV using the remote in the Google TV app.
It would have been super useful if the Google TV remote was also available on the Apple Watch, unfortunately it is not.
There is no other means to use a remote on the watch to control Google TV devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Return&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Apple Watch is a beautifully crafted product, but I felt like its current version was just not working for me due to these reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apps install requires password typing:
The biggest absurdity of the Apple Watch is that I can only install apps from the watch, not from its Watch app on the iPhone.
And it asks for my Apple password to install - there is no way I am going to try to enter my cryptic random-generated password using that handwriting input on the watch!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Way too much stuff going on with its UI:
there are Live Actions, widgets if you swipe from below, apps if you click the crown and the Control Center if you click the side button.
Just think about it for a moment - this device display UI has more complexity than MacOS (on computer) and iOS (on the phone/tablet).
I am surprised that Apple does not realize how complex the UI/UX is in this device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Battery life:
Sucks.
Apple expects me to wear this all day and night, but it does not last more than a day - so Apple when do I charge it?
I am absolutely not going to charge a watch every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step count:
All I wanted to track was a step count, but Apple seems to hate the step count.
They have these weird 3 color bars that show your activity for the day.
Just by looking at the color and a minimalistic icon they have, how am I supposed to know what each color is tracking?
And the step count is always hidden, making you step through multiple screens to view it.
There is no watch face where Apple will show the step count.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strap:
I spent an hour at the Apple store and the least worst strap I could pick was the Nike velcro one.
The rubber ones are soft, but they have a weird clasp that is super hard to use.
I cannot fathom why they could not provide at least one strap that uses the normal watch clasp.
The leather and metal ones are all too irritating for my skin, so I avoid those.
So, there we are with Nike velcro and even after a week it still felt itchy and don't even get me started on how ugly this strap is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apps picking is tiresome:
You get 2 views of the apps - a beehive-like hexagonal grid or a scroll list of apps.
The hexagonal grid is irritating, I would have preferred a regular grid (like on the phone) and bigger icons (they are way too small).
The scroll list of apps is frustrating because while Apple allows me to reorder the hexagonal grid, I cannot reorder the app list - so I need to scroll in alphabetical order to reach the bottom apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Widgets:
I could not figure out how to control the order of badges or which apps they are originating from.
And Apple suddenly uses AI to add some Live Actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crown:
This is super hard to use - because in an analog watch you remove the watch from your wrist to wind it up or change the time using the crown.
Apple borrowed the crown idea without thinking through that they are making the crown a primary interface though it is hard to turn it while the watch is on the wrist.
Also, I can already scroll with touch on the display, so why do I need the crown again?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shape:
I could not get over the chunky squarish shape of the watch.
I prefer a round or hexagonal shape for a watch and though Apple has so many watches, not a single one is round.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-09-21-apple-watch-se-3.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2025 03:44:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finder Cheatsheet</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-05-07-finder-cheatsheet.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Finder&lt;/strong&gt; is the file manager in MacOS.
Its logo is a smiling face and called the &lt;em&gt;Happy Mac&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cut and paste files&lt;/strong&gt;:
Files cannot be cut in Finder.
Instead, copy the files (&lt;code&gt;command c&lt;/code&gt;) and while pasting in the destination directory use &lt;code&gt;option command v&lt;/code&gt;.
This special paste moves the files instead of copying them over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quit Finder from Dock&lt;/strong&gt;:
Finder always seems to be running in the Dock.
Apparently, it cannot be quit and will always be running in the Dock.
Even when killed, it will be respawned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hide disks from desktop&lt;/strong&gt;:
Go to Finder -&amp;gt; Settings -&amp;gt; General.
Under &lt;em&gt;Show these items on the desktop&lt;/em&gt;, uncheck all the types of disks and servers you would like to be hidden on the desktop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tried with:&lt;/strong&gt; Finder 15.3 and MacOS Sequoia 15.3&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-05-07-finder-cheatsheet.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 13:09:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MacOS Terminal</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-04-29-macos-terminal.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Terminal&lt;/strong&gt; is the default terminal application on MacOS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Change font size temporarily&lt;/strong&gt;:
Press &lt;code&gt;command +&lt;/code&gt; to increase, &lt;code&gt;command -&lt;/code&gt; to decrease and &lt;code&gt;command 0&lt;/code&gt; to reset the font size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Change font size persistently&lt;/strong&gt;:
Go to Settings -&amp;gt; Profiles and change the font size for the profile you use.
The font size change is not yet applied, until you right-click on the terminal window, choose Inspector and choose the profile again.
The change will also be applied the next time Terminal is opened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tried with:&lt;/strong&gt; Terminal 2.14 and MacOS Sequoia 15.2&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-04-29-macos-terminal.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 05:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MacOS Cheatsheet</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-04-24-macos-cheatsheet.html</link>
      <description>&lt;h1&gt;Desktop&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dock&lt;/strong&gt;:
Located at the bottom of the desktop and holds the pinned applications and open applications.
The running applications have a dot displayed under them.
There are some default applications like Finder (leftmost icon) and Downloads and Trash (rightmost icons).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mission Control&lt;/strong&gt;:
Shows all the desktop &lt;em&gt;spaces&lt;/em&gt; at the top and the windows of all the open applications in the current space.
It is basically the view of windows we see with &lt;code&gt;alt tab&lt;/code&gt; in Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To open Mission Control use &lt;code&gt;ctrl up&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To move between spaces use &lt;code&gt;ctrl right&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;ctrl left&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create a new space, open Mission Control and click the &lt;code&gt;+&lt;/code&gt; at the top-right corner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To move a window to a different space, open Mission Control and drag window to the destination space in the top bar.
Windows has keyboard shortcuts to move a window to a different space, but MacOS does not have shortcut for this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Keyboard Shortcuts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MacOS keyboard shortcuts use the special 4 keys on the Apple keyboard (L to R): &lt;code&gt;fn&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;control&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;option&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;command&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the keyboard shortcuts are visible beside the toolbar menu option when you choose them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;command space&lt;/code&gt;: Opens Spotlight, that can be used to launch applications and open files by typing their name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;command tab&lt;/code&gt;: Switch between currently open applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;control command f&lt;/code&gt;: Maximize the current application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;command w&lt;/code&gt;: Close the window. Other windows of an application will still be open and the application will continue to run in the background (even if its final window is closed).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;command q&lt;/code&gt;: Quit the application and all its windows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;control command q&lt;/code&gt;: Lock the screen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Common operations&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Full screen window&lt;/strong&gt;:
To toggle the current window to full screen and back use &lt;code&gt;control command f&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maximize window&lt;/strong&gt;:
Window can be maximized (or &lt;em&gt;Zoom&lt;/em&gt; as MacOS calls it) by double-clicking on the titlebar.
The keyboard shortcut is &lt;code&gt;fn control f&lt;/code&gt;, but weirdly it only maximizes, but does not toggle back the window shape.
I prefer going to Settings -&amp;gt; Keyboard -&amp;gt; Keyboard Shortcuts -&amp;gt; App Shortcuts and under &lt;em&gt;All Applications&lt;/em&gt;, add a keyboard shortcut with Menu title &lt;code&gt;Zoom&lt;/code&gt; and a custom keyboard shortcut such as &lt;code&gt;shift command m&lt;/code&gt;.
This keyboard shortcut both maximizes and toggles back the window shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tile window&lt;/strong&gt;:
Hold the pointer over the top-left green button of the current window and in the &lt;em&gt;Move &amp;amp; Resize&lt;/em&gt; section choose which vertical or horizontal half of the current space the window should be moved and resized to.
For moving and tiling to a quadrant, hold the pointer over the top-left green button and press &lt;code&gt;option&lt;/code&gt; button, the 4 possible quadrant positions are displayed to choose from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keyboard shortcuts for moving windows&lt;/strong&gt;:
MacOS does not have default keyboard shortcuts to move windows to left/right/top/bottom half of window.
But those keyboard shortcuts can be added in Settings -&amp;gt; Keyboard -&amp;gt; Keyboard Shortcuts -&amp;gt; App Shortcuts -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;All Applications&lt;/em&gt; using the following Menu Titles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Left&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;option left&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Right&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;option right&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Top&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;option up&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Bottom&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;option down&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Insert emoji&lt;/strong&gt;:
On the Macbook Pro keyboard, the &lt;code&gt;Fn&lt;/code&gt; key brings up the emoji picker.
When using a USB/Windows keyboard, pressing &lt;code&gt;control command space&lt;/code&gt; does the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Show scroll bars&lt;/strong&gt;:
To always show a scroll bar in windows, go to System Settings -&amp;gt; Appearance.
For &lt;em&gt;Show scroll bars&lt;/em&gt; choose the option &lt;em&gt;Always&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moving in text&lt;/strong&gt;:
Macbook Pro keyboard does not have Home and End buttons.
So, use &lt;code&gt;command left&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;command right&lt;/code&gt; to move to start and end of current line of text.
Similarly, use &lt;code&gt;shift command left&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;shift command right&lt;/code&gt; to mark up to left or right end of line of text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Change key repeat speed&lt;/strong&gt;:
I found it slow to move through text in editor with left-right&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take screenshot&lt;/strong&gt;:
Press &lt;code&gt;shift command 4&lt;/code&gt; to draw section of screen to capture.
Thumbnail of captured image appears at bottom-right of display for editing.
The image is saved to the Desktop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Find IP address&lt;/strong&gt;:
Open Terminal and type &lt;code&gt;ifconfig&lt;/code&gt;.
Look for the IP address listed for the &lt;code&gt;en0&lt;/code&gt; network interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lock the screen when lid is closed&lt;/strong&gt;:
Go to System Settings -&amp;gt; Lock Screen.
Set the option &lt;em&gt;Require password after screen saver begins or display is turned off&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Immediately&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remap Windows keyboard keys&lt;/strong&gt;:
When I connect a USB Windows keyboard, its Win key is mapped to Command and its Alt key is mapped to Option.
To swap the Win and Alt key mappings, go to System Settings -&amp;gt; Keyboard -&amp;gt; Keyboard Shortcuts.
In the dialog, choose Modifier Keys and in the Select keyboard option choose &lt;em&gt;USB keyboard&lt;/em&gt;.
For Option key, pick Command.
For Command key, pick Option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Change default mail application&lt;/strong&gt;:
Apple Mail is the default mail application.
To change the default to a different mail application (like Outlook) you still need to open Apple Mail and have an account in there.
Go to menu bar, choose Mail -&amp;gt; Settings.
Go to General -&amp;gt; Default email reader and set to a different mail app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Switch between windows&lt;/strong&gt;:
The &lt;code&gt;cmd tab&lt;/code&gt; keyboard shortcut only switches between apps, not the individual windows, while I prefer to switch between windows (just like in Windows).
AltTab is a fantastic open-source tool that can be used to switch between all windows.
It can be customized to run at startup from the menubar, work with any keyboard shortcut (I like to replace &lt;code&gt;cmd tab&lt;/code&gt; with this) and it can display the windows as thumbnails, app icons or titles, all in 3 different sizes (small/medium/large).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Change name of Bluetooth device&lt;/strong&gt;:
Some Bluetooth devices have associated software that can be used to change their name.
If they do not, then their name to MacOS at least can be changed in the OS.
To do this, open the Bluetooth settings, and click the (i) to the right of the device name.
In the dialog that pops up, change the device name and press Return.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tried with:&lt;/strong&gt; MacOS Sequoia 15.2&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-04-24-macos-cheatsheet.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 05:47:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Macbook Pro</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-04-24-macbook-pro.html</link>
      <description>&lt;h1&gt;External displays&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dell C3422WE&lt;/strong&gt;:
This is a curved display with an integrated USB hub.
It was straightforward to connect this display to the MBP using the display's USB-C cable.
The display was usable as an extended display when the MBP lid was open.
The display was also usable as the sole display when the MBP lid was closed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dell WD19TBS, P3424WEB and U2415&lt;/strong&gt;:
In this setup, two displays (P3424WEB and U2415) were connected to the WD19TBS dock using DisplayPort and HDMI respectively, and the USB-C cable of the dock was plugged into MBP.
In this mode, MBP could recognize only the U2415 and mirrored the content on the P3424WEB.
Apparently, MBP supports 2 external displays in addition to its own display, but it requires at least one of those to be connected using ThunderBolt into the USB dock.
As as alternate solution, I plugged the U2415's DisplayPort directly into the MBP as a second input and was able to use both displays after that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-04-24-macbook-pro.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 05:47:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thorium Reader</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-02-21-thorium-reader.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently had to open a complex EPUB file with fixed layout of images and overlaid text.
None of the regular ebook readers on Linux, like Calibre or FBReader could do the job.
&lt;a href="https://www.edrlab.org/software/thorium-reader/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thorium Reader&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; turned out to be the one which accomplished the task perfectly.
This software is open-sourced on Github &lt;a href="https://github.com/edrlab/thorium-reader"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install&lt;/strong&gt;:
I downloaded the &lt;code&gt;.deb&lt;/code&gt; file for the latest release from &lt;a href="https://github.com/edrlab/thorium-reader/releases"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and installed it at the shell:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo dpkg -i EDRLab.ThoriumReader_3.1.0_amd64.deb
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sandbox error&lt;/strong&gt;:
Running Thorium for the first time, gave me the all-familiar sandbox error.
Fixing that was simple:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo chown root:root /opt/Thorium/chrome-sandbox

$ sudo chmod 4755 /opt/Thorium/chrome-sandbox
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tried with&lt;/strong&gt;: Thorium Reader 3.1.0 and Ubuntu 24.04&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-02-21-thorium-reader.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 04:39:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tech links of February 2025</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-02-01-tech-links-of-february-2025.html</link>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rCwgAGG2sZQ"&gt;RTX 5090 chip deep-dive&lt;/a&gt;:
High Yield channel looks into the NVIDIA RTX 5090 (GB202) die to understand what it is composed of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mtlynch.io/solo-developer-year-7/"&gt;My Seventh Year as a Bootstrapped Founder&lt;/a&gt;:
I have been following Michael Lynch's indie journey since he left Google.
In his latest annual post, he shared that he sold his TinyPilot venture and how that went down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QEJpZjg8GuA"&gt;Algorithms are breaking how we think&lt;/a&gt;:
On &lt;em&gt;algorithm complacency&lt;/em&gt;, people choosing to get their information from recommendation algorithms instead of curating their own feed.
A good example is people choosing Youtube's recommendation feed (the default) instead of their &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/feed/subscriptions"&gt;subscriptions feed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-02-01-tech-links-of-february-2025.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 17:31:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tech links of January 2025</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-01-02-tech-links-of-january-2025.html</link>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ubc.ca.panopto.com/Panopto/Pages/Viewer.aspx?id=880a1d92-30d7-4683-80e7-b1e000f501d3"&gt;Death and Life in Silicon Valley&lt;/a&gt;:
Erik Lindholm's retirement talk about his 35-year career at SGI and NVIDIA.
Covers his early personal life, work in Japan, SGI and move to NVIDIA.
Creation of T&amp;amp;L unit in GPU (instead of CPU), launch of GeForce 256 (Geometry Force) GPU, vertex/pixel shaders, unified shaders, warp to work on packed 16 vertices/pixels and road to SIMT/CUDA.
Highly recommended watch for graphics and CUDA enthusiasts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.xyplorer.com/faq-topic.php?id=VB6"&gt;Is XYplorer really written in VB6?&lt;/a&gt;:
Short history of Visual Basic, why XYplorer is written (and successful) in it to this day and some of its real limitations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://matduggan.com/stop-trying-to-schedule-a-call-with-me/"&gt;Stop Trying To Schedule A Call With Me&lt;/a&gt;:
Humorous telling of the journey of a typical relationship between an engineer and the startup whose product he tries out to solve a problem.
I have been on &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; sides of this relationship, so I know it's true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3IESh12AQw4"&gt;Furnace - How to Relight a Pilot Light&lt;/a&gt;:
This video shows the pilot light and thermocouple in a gas furnace used for heating homes in the US and how they work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n76kz1tcjtw"&gt;How A Gas Furnace Works&lt;/a&gt;:
Animated schematic of how a gas furnace works at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2025-01-02-tech-links-of-january-2025.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 21:04:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tech links of December 2024</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-12-24-tech-links-of-december-2024.html</link>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vc4yL3YTwWk"&gt;Exposing the Honey Influencer Scam&lt;/a&gt;:
Youtube influencers promoted the Honey browser extension informing users they could get coupons and discounts on their online purchases when they used it.
Turns out that Honey was actually overriding and grabbing the affiliate money and other fradulent and nefarious practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://chaos.social/@Error/113650831365024417"&gt;Classic x86 system bus topology&lt;/a&gt;:
Subway diagram of placement of Northbridge, Southbridge and FSB (Front Side Bus) that connected CPU to GPU, DDR memory, SATA storage, PCIe devices and USB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://avi.im/blag/2024/sqlite-facts/"&gt;Collection of insane and fun facts about SQLite&lt;/a&gt;: Most deployed DB (trillion copies) maintained by 3 contributors and other insane facts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-12-24-tech-links-of-december-2024.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 20:35:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BlueSky</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-11-27-bluesky.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BlueSky&lt;/strong&gt; is an online service similar to Twitter to read, repost and share small posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Signup&lt;/strong&gt;:
Sign up for an account at &lt;a href="https://bsky.app/"&gt;bsky.app&lt;/a&gt;.
Choose &lt;em&gt;Bluesky&lt;/em&gt; as the &lt;em&gt;service&lt;/em&gt; and your Bluesky ID will be &lt;code&gt;@codeyarns.bluesky.social&lt;/code&gt;.
If you are able to provide a custom service provider, then your Bluesky ID will be &lt;code&gt;@codeyarns.&amp;lt;something&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Online webpage&lt;/strong&gt;:
Once signed up, you can read, repost and share posts online at &lt;a href="https://bsky.app/profile/codeyarns.bsky.social"&gt;&lt;code&gt;bsky.app/profile/codeyarns.bsky.social&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow&lt;/strong&gt;:
The accounts you follow will appear as &lt;em&gt;following&lt;/em&gt; on your profile.
The accounts that follow you will appear as &lt;em&gt;followers&lt;/em&gt; on your profile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feeds&lt;/strong&gt;:
Posts from your &lt;em&gt;following&lt;/em&gt; accounts will appear in the default &lt;em&gt;Following&lt;/em&gt; feed.
You can also find and add other custom feeds like &lt;em&gt;Followers&lt;/em&gt; (posts of your followers), &lt;em&gt;Mutuals&lt;/em&gt; (posts from mutually following accounts), &lt;em&gt;Mentions&lt;/em&gt; (only posts that mention you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lists&lt;/strong&gt;:
You can add accounts to one or more lists you create at &lt;a href="https://bsky.app/lists"&gt;bsky.app/lists&lt;/a&gt;.
Even accounts that you do not follow can be added to lists.
I find this a handy way to categorize my following into lists and not have their posts appear in the main Following feed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Posts&lt;/strong&gt;:
Posts have a 300 character limit and they cannot be edited once posted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tags&lt;/strong&gt;:
Posts can have hashtags.
Posts of a specific hashtag can be viewed at &lt;a href="https://bsky.app/hashtag/TheEconomist"&gt;bsky.app/hashtag/TheEconomist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bridging&lt;/strong&gt;:
For details on how to bridge from Bluesky to Mastodon or from Mastodon to Bluesky, see &lt;a href="2022-11-06-mastodon.html"&gt;my Mastodon post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-11-27-bluesky.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 17:53:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Apple iPad Mini 6</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-11-14-apple-ipad-mini-6.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My experiment with a &lt;a href="2023-02-27-lenovo-tab-m7.html"&gt;small tablet&lt;/a&gt; as ebook reader worked out so well that I decided to upgrade to an &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPad_Mini_(6th_generation)"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apple iPad Mini (6th generation)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;em&gt;Starlight&lt;/em&gt; color.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Specifications&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;iPadOS: 17.5.1 (21F90)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model number: MK7P3LL/A&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buttons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Top left: Vol up/down&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Top right: Power / Touch ID&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connectivity: USB-C at bottom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bluetooth: 5.0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wifi: 6 802.11ax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SoC: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple_A15"&gt;A15 Bionic&lt;/a&gt; 2.92 GHz (6-core CPU, 5-core  GPU, 16-core Neural Engine)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Display: 8.3-inch 2266x1488 Liquid Retina (326 PPI)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Front camera: 12 MP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rear camera: 12 MP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;User Interface&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Home Screen&lt;/strong&gt;:
Similar to desktop on computers, the main central region of display where the app icons are shown.
Swipe up from the bottom edge of screen to get the home screen.
It can have multiple pages, swipe left or right to navigate the pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;App Library&lt;/strong&gt;:
Swipe left past all the pages to get this.
Shows all the installed apps organized into categories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dock&lt;/strong&gt;:
Swipe up from the bottom edge only a little bit to reveal the Dock at the bottom.
It shows the most recently used apps, the right-most button is the App Library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;App Switcher&lt;/strong&gt;:
Swipe up from the bottom edge, stop in the center of the display and hold to get the App Switcher.
Swipe up on an app to quit it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Control center&lt;/strong&gt;:
Shown when you swipe down from top-left part of display.
Provides quick access to common settings like wifi, bluetooth, brightness and rotation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Split view&lt;/strong&gt;:
Feature used to display 2 apps side by side.
Only available on iPads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lock Screen&lt;/strong&gt;:
Press and hold on the lock screen to get the customize option.
Create and customize your own lock screen here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Widgets&lt;/strong&gt;:
Like app buttons, but can be larger and show information from inside an app directly on the Home Screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Folder&lt;/strong&gt;:
Drag one app on another to open up a new Folder that holds both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Usage&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Search&lt;/strong&gt;:
Swipe down from the middle of the screen to get search.
Works both from Home Screen or the Lock Screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/102597"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use as second display for Macbook&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:
Having the iPad Mini as a second display (&lt;strong&gt;sidecar&lt;/strong&gt;) is useful not just as additional screen estate for windows, but to use the Apple Pencil (or similar writing device) to jot notes, annotate or draw through iPad in any Macbook app that supports it.
First, make sure both the Macbook and iPad are signed into the same Apple account and both the devices are visible in &lt;strong&gt;Devices&lt;/strong&gt; section of the account in both of them.
Next, make sure the devices are near each other and on the same wifi network.
Connecting the iPad with USB-C cable to the Macbook is a better solution.
Finally, choose the iPad in the &lt;strong&gt;Screen Mirroring&lt;/strong&gt; option on the Macbook and further in the &lt;strong&gt;Displays&lt;/strong&gt; settings you can choose if you want to mirror or extend the display to the iPad.
Note that finger touch does not work on the iPad when it is in this mode, only the Macbook's mouse/trackpad and the iPad's Pencil will work (useful for drawing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/ipad/welcome/ipados"&gt;iPad User Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-11-14-apple-ipad-mini-6.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 04:19:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Powkiddy RGB30</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-02-12-powkiddy-rgb30.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://powkiddy.com/products/pre-sale-powkiddy-rgb30-rk3566-handheld-game-console-built-in-wifi"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Powkiddy RGB30&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a handheld game console that can be used to emulate games from the retro game consoles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Specifications&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Size: 145 x 86.5 x 18 mm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weight: 207g&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Display size: 4.0-inch IPS OCA full fit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Display resolution: 720 * 720&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CPU: Rock-Chips RK3566, ARM quad-core 1.8GHz&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RAM: LPDDR4 1GB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;External storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TF1-OS: MicroSD card up to 256GB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TF2-Game: MicroSD card up to 256GB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wifi: WIFI 5G and Bluetooth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Loudspeaker: 1W * 2 cavity loudspeaker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Battery: 4100mA li-polymer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Input power: 5V-2A&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maximum power consumption: 5W&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Battery life: 8 hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charging time: 2 hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interfaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USB: TYPE-C fast charging interface&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TV HD interface&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OTG-USB interface&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3.5mm earphone interface&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Keyboard shortcuts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Main menu: &lt;code&gt;Start&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quit game: &lt;code&gt;Select + Start&lt;/code&gt; 2 times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Attempt 1: Using shipped JELOS (Feb 2024)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The device shipped with &lt;a href="https://github.com/JustEnoughLinuxOS"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Just Enough Linux OS (JELOS)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; v20230612.
It took several minutes for the JELOS bootup logo to show up and several more minutes for it to finish its initial configuration.
The first time, I pressed some keys while waiting and it showed some ncurses configuration screens and flickered.
I somehow got it to boot by inserting an empty micro SD card in the TFGAME slot and rebooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reboot, JELOS would not create the game directories in the TFGAME micro SD card even though I requested it using the Main Menu -&amp;gt; System Settings -&amp;gt; Create game directories option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gave up and instead copied over the rom files into console directories inside the &lt;code&gt;/storage/roms&lt;/code&gt; on the main TFOS micro SD card.
This worked and the games showed up on reboot and the games worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No audio&lt;/strong&gt;:
However, there was absolutely no audio!
I scoured all the search results and tried all the solutions, but to no avail.
Finally, the solution that restored audio was to do a fresh installation of the latest version of JELOS.
See the next section for details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Attempt 2: Using fresh JELOS (Feb 2024)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get around the problems I faced with the default software, I installed the latest version of JELOS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do not use the micro SD card provided by the manufacturer.
This is a no-name brand card.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get 2 micro SD cards, one for the OS and the other for the games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Download the latest OS image from &lt;em&gt;Releases&lt;/em&gt; that has RK3566 in its filename and unzip the &lt;code&gt;.img&lt;/code&gt; file.
Flash this to the OS micro SD card.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Format the TFGAME micro SD card as FAT or exFAT and create a &lt;code&gt;roms&lt;/code&gt; directory on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Insert &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; the micro SD cards into the device for the first boot.
During its initial configuration, JELOS should use the TFGAME micro SD card as its &lt;em&gt;external&lt;/em&gt; source of game directories.
Note: If you do not have both cards inserted for the OS setup, it will use the OS card for its game directories.
And it would not use the TFGAME card no matter if I had a &lt;code&gt;roms&lt;/code&gt; directory on it and asked it to create game directories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to Main Menu -&amp;gt; System Settings -&amp;gt; Create game directories.
You must see the TFGAME card listed as the &lt;em&gt;external&lt;/em&gt; game source under Main Menu -&amp;gt; System Settings -&amp;gt; Information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you can copy roms to the respective console directory, for example &lt;code&gt;/roms/nes&lt;/code&gt;, in the TFGAME card.
When inserted back into the device, the console and its games should automatically appear for playing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Attempt 3: Using ROCKNIX (Dec 2024)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the JELOS was abandoned in March 2024 and all its binary releases were removed online.
A fork called &lt;a href="https://github.com/ROCKNIX"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ROCKNIX&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was started later and I switched to it in December 2024 with the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I downloaded the latest release file &lt;code&gt;ROCKNIX-RK3566.aarch64-20241120-Generic.img.gz&lt;/code&gt; from its &lt;a href="https://github.com/ROCKNIX/distribution/releases/tag/20241120"&gt;Releases page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used the original 4GB micro-SD card used for the JELOS OS earlier and tried to install image ROCKNIX on it using Rufus.
But it kept getting &lt;em&gt;write errors&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead I used a 64GB micro-SD card and the imaging went through successfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I removed the games micro-SD card from the console and inserted only this newly imaged micro-SD card and booted up the device successfully.
I shut it down and put in my original games micro-SD card, restarted and all the games were available too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Usage&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SSH&lt;/strong&gt;:
Enable ** in Main Menu -&amp;gt; Network Settings.
SSH into the device from a computer using &lt;code&gt;ssh root@&amp;lt;ip address&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;linux&lt;/code&gt; as password.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://retrogamecorps.com/2023/10/27/powkiddy-rgb30-starter-guide/"&gt;Retro Game Corps - Powkiddy RGB30 Starter Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/ROCKNIX/distribution/blob/20241120/documentation/PER_DEVICE_DOCUMENTATION/RK3566/SUPPORTED_EMULATORS_AND_CORES.md"&gt;ROCKNIX RK3566 Supported Systems, Emulators and Cores&lt;/a&gt;:
Comprehensive table of consoles, roms directory name and supported file extensions.
Table is sorted by the manufacturer name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-02-12-powkiddy-rgb30.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 21:23:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RayHom RM-39 Battery Charger</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-02-03-rayhom-rm39.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RayHom RM-39&lt;/strong&gt; is a charger for rechargeable NiMH batteries.
It handles all the battery formats that are typically used at home: AAA, AA, C, D and 9V.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Battery types&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of batteries of each type that can be charged at the same time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AAA&lt;/strong&gt;: 4 x 1.2V&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AA&lt;/strong&gt;: 4 x 1.2V&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt;: 4 x 1.2V&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt;: 4 x 1.2V&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9V Cell&lt;/strong&gt;: 2 x 9V&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Notes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a nice LCD display on the front that displays the current charge level of each of the batteries.
It flashes while the battery is being charged and shows a non-flashing steady display when the battery is done being charged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its charging speed of the common AAA and AA batteries is pretty slow.
My &lt;strong&gt;Panasonic BQ-CC55&lt;/strong&gt; can charge these types in a fraction of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-02-03-rayhom-rm39.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Feb 2024 05:33:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kate's Grammar Tool (KGT)</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-02-03-kgt.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/katef/kgt"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kate's Grammar Tool (KGT)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a swiss-army knife to handle the various BNF grammar files and visualize them as railroad diagrams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source code&lt;/strong&gt;:
KGT is open source and its source code is available at https://github.com/katef/kgt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build&lt;/strong&gt;:
Instructions to build this tool:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git clone git@github.com:katef/kgt.git
$ cd kgt
$ bmake -r
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This produces the binary &lt;code&gt;build/bin/kgt&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product railroad diagrams&lt;/strong&gt;:
To produce railroad diagrams for a ABNF file in ASCII text, UTF8 or SVG formats:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ kgt -l abnf -e rrtext &amp;lt; in.abnf &amp;gt; out.txt

$ kgt -l abnf -e rrutf8 &amp;lt; in.abnf &amp;gt; out.txt

$ kgt -l abnf -e svg    &amp;lt; in.abnf &amp;gt; out.svg
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-02-03-kgt.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Feb 2024 05:24:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PuTTY cheatsheet</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-01-22-putty.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/putty/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PuTTY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a popular SSH client for Windows.
It was created by and is maintained by &lt;a href="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simon Tatham&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install&lt;/strong&gt;:
Download and install the latest version of PuTTY from &lt;a href="https://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/putty/latest.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Help&lt;/strong&gt;:
There are a lot of configuration options in the PuTTY launch window.
To get detailed help about all these options, click the &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt; at the top-right of the window and click on the option you want help for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sessions&lt;/strong&gt;:
Configuration related to a host can be stored together in PuTTY as a &lt;em&gt;session&lt;/em&gt;.
However, the UI for this is a bit non-intuitive, here is a primer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To &lt;strong&gt;create&lt;/strong&gt; a session: type a name in the &lt;em&gt;Saved Sessions&lt;/em&gt; textbox, provide its hostname, port and connection type. Click the &lt;em&gt;Save&lt;/em&gt; button to save this session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To &lt;strong&gt;load&lt;/strong&gt; a session: select its name in the session list and press the &lt;em&gt;Load&lt;/em&gt; button. This loads the configuration values of this session into all the categories listed in the sidebar on the left.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To &lt;strong&gt;configure&lt;/strong&gt; a session: load the session, click through the categories in the left sidebar and set the values you desire. Remember to go back to the &lt;em&gt;Session&lt;/em&gt; category and click the &lt;em&gt;Save&lt;/em&gt; button to save this configuration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To &lt;strong&gt;open&lt;/strong&gt; a session: choose the session in the list and either double-click it or click the &lt;em&gt;Open&lt;/em&gt; button. This opens a SSH connection with the host of that session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cursor&lt;/strong&gt;:
Find this configuration under Window -&amp;gt; Appearance.
I like the &lt;em&gt;vertical line&lt;/em&gt; with the &lt;em&gt;cursor blinks&lt;/em&gt; enabled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Font&lt;/strong&gt;:
Find this configuration under Window -&amp;gt; Appearance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tried with&lt;/strong&gt;: PuTTY 0.80&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-01-22-putty.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2024 22:14:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SpoTube</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-01-20-spotube.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://spotube.krtirtho.dev/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SpoTube&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a music player application that combined the data API from Spotify to play songs from Youtube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source code&lt;/strong&gt;:
This is an open source application and its source code is available on Github at https://github.com/KRTirtho/spotube/.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install&lt;/strong&gt;:
For Ubuntu, download the latest DEB file the &lt;a href="https://github.com/KRTirtho/spotube/releases/"&gt;releases&lt;/a&gt;.
Install it using:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo install ./Spotube-linux-x86_64.deb
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Login&lt;/strong&gt;:
Login into Spotify on Firefox.
Press &lt;code&gt;F12&lt;/code&gt; to open the Developer Tools.
Click on Storage -&amp;gt; Cookies and from the &lt;code&gt;https://open.spotify.com&lt;/code&gt; entry copy the &lt;code&gt;sp_dc&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;sp_key&lt;/code&gt; values.
Choose to login in SpoTube and enter these values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Usage&lt;/strong&gt;:
Once logged into SpoTube, search songs, add them to playlists and play them.
Everything is effected on the actual Spotify account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tried with&lt;/strong&gt;: SpoTube 3.4.0 and Ubuntu 22.04&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-01-20-spotube.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2024 22:51:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microsoft Family Safety</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-01-15-microsoft-family-safety.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microsoft_family_features"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Microsoft Family Safety&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is the name of all their Windows, web and phone applications used for parental control of children when they use their Windows computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Applications&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Family Safety app is available for Android &lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.microsoft.familysafety"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and for iOS &lt;a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/microsoft-family-safety/id1489209093"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can also be accessed online at https://account.microsoft.com/family/home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be accessed on the Windows computer of the parent in the Settings, type &lt;em&gt;Family Safety&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add a child&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To enable this for the child's Windows 11 computer, it is ideal if the parent already has an administrator account on it and the child is a non-admin local user who logs in with a Microsoft account (not a local account).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to the Family Safety app on the child's computer and enable it. The parents might need to follow the process on their Family Safety app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Screen Time&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click on the child's name and the &lt;em&gt;Screen Time&lt;/em&gt; section to set their screen time limits and their current usage graph.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The screen time limit can be set on individual devices of this child or the sum across all their devices.
  It can be set the same or differently for the days of the week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Windows on the child's computer will lock up when the time limit for the day is reached.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windows shows a button on the locked computer for the child to request more time from the parent. If the child choose that, the parents gets a prompt in the &lt;em&gt;Notification&lt;/em&gt; section of Family Safety. They can give more screen time by responding to this notification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lock a device&lt;/strong&gt;:
In the Family Safety app, choose the child, go to Screen Time and choose &lt;em&gt;Lock devices&lt;/em&gt; to lock a device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-01-15-microsoft-family-safety.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 19:05:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dive tool for Docker</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-01-09-dive.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/wagoodman/dive"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a visual tool to explore the layers and contents of a Docker image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://github.com/wagoodman/dive#installation"&gt;installation instructions&lt;/a&gt; for Ubuntu from the Github README is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ export DIVE_VERSION=$(curl -sL &amp;quot;https://api.github.com/repos/wagoodman/dive/releases/latest&amp;quot; | grep '&amp;quot;tag_name&amp;quot;:' | sed -E 's/.*&amp;quot;v([^&amp;quot;]+)&amp;quot;.*/\1/')
$ curl -OL https://github.com/wagoodman/dive/releases/download/v${DIVE_VERSION}/dive_${DIVE_VERSION}_linux_amd64.deb
$ sudo apt install ./dive_${DIVE_VERSION}_linux_amd64.deb
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Usage&lt;/strong&gt;:
Invoke on any image name that you have already pulled to your computer.
For example:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ docker pull alpine

$ dive alpine
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Layers are displayed on the left. Use arrow keys to move up and down.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contents of the selected layer are displayed on the right. Use arrow keys to move, &lt;code&gt;Space&lt;/code&gt; to collapse or expand a directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;code&gt;Tab&lt;/code&gt; to switch between layers and contents views.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tried with&lt;/strong&gt;: Dive 0.11.0, Docker 25.0.5 and Ubuntu 22.04&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-01-09-dive.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 03:41:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AI Search extension for Firefox</title>
      <link>https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-01-09-ai-search.html</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Perplexity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is one of the many new startups that offer web search powered by LLMs and DL.
The &lt;a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/ai-search/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AI Search&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; extension for Firefox brings that search capability directly into the browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install&lt;/strong&gt;:
Install the extension from &lt;a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/ai-search/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Usage&lt;/strong&gt;:
Clicking the extension's button from the toolbar opens a sidebar where your search query to Perplexity can be entered.
There does not seem to be any way to set a keyboard shortcut for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Search engine&lt;/strong&gt;:
The extension also adds Perplexity into the list of Firefox search engines.
Go to the Firefox search settings to set Perplexity as the default search engine from the dropdown or move its position among the rest of the engines.
Perplexity can also be used for searching by typing &lt;code&gt;@AI&lt;/code&gt; in the addressbar and then type in the rest of the search query.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tried with&lt;/strong&gt;: AI Search 0.2 and Firefox 121.0&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://codeyarns.com/tech/2024-01-09-ai-search.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 03:26:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
